Guide to the New York City 100 Records 1995-2000 (Bulk 1997-1999) MS 444
New-York Historical Society
The New York City 100 Records
1995-2000 (Bulk 1997-1999)
New-York Historical Society
MS 444
8.5 Linear feet (18 boxes, 3 volumes)
The New York City 100 Records documents the activities of the nonprofit institution "The New York City 100." A public-private collaboration, the organization was created to focus on a year of New York history and to coordinate the centennial celebration of Greater New York's consolidation. Records describe organizational structure and participants; background and planning; fundraising; events and programs; partnerships; educational outreach; public relations and advertising; accounting and finance; spin off products and licensing; and press coverage.
Historical Note
The New York City 100 (1997-2000) was a nonprofit institution created as a public-private collaboration whose mission was to plan and coordinate commemoration of the centennial of the creation of "Greater New York" -- the consolidation of forty municipalities, including the separate cities of Brooklyn and New York, on January 1, 1898. (This merger insured New York's place as America's largest city and, in the world, second only to London. The city's size tripled, to 320 square miles, and its population doubled to 3.4 million.)
Timeline
1995 Centennial celebration idea conceived by Betsy Gotbaum, then Executive Director of the New-York Historical Society, and Ric Burns, President of Steeplechase Films.
1997 New York City 100 non-profit incorporated as NYC 1898-1998 Centennial Celebration Inc.; DBA NYC 100, Inc.
May 13, 1997 Kick-off Fundraiser hosted by Arthur Gelb, president of the New York Times Foundation.
July 1, 1997 Marie Salerno named President and Executive Director.
August 9, 1997 Fundraiser and preview of New York documentary hosted by Ric Burns.
September 8, 1997 Gracie Mansion Announcement Event.
December 1998-December 1999 NYC 100 produces a Centennial Celebration in which the City of New York collaborated with a consortium of New York's major cultural, educational and historic institutions, and national public television. Events included performances, concerts, parades, exhibitions, sporting and other public programs under a single umbrella, under the centennial official logo. Celebration also included integration of the centennial into the public school curriculum, establishment of a Web site and creation of spin-off products.
December 31, 1997 Major Event - New Years Eve at Times Square followed by Mayoral Inauguration.
June 19-21, 1998 Major Event - Centennial Weekend.
July 10, 1998 Major Event - Concert on the Great Lawn, Central Park.
January-December 1999 Extension of the celebration into 1999 – a second year of programming called "America Begins in New York" based on the immigrant experience. Among its activities were creation of teacher resource materials, walking tours, essay and poster contests and creation of The New York Pop-Up Book.
1999 Nationwide broadcast of New York documentary film by Ric Burns.
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains a wide variety of materials accumulated during the life of the New York City 100 organization. Most of the materials are outlined in "Final Report for the archive of The New-York Historical Society" prepared by Marie Salerno, President, New York City 100.
Among the document types are correspondence, plans and drafts of plans, funding proposals, press releases, lists of individuals (staff, donors, invitees, participants), photographs, news clippings, advertisements, graphics, posters, mock-ups and final version of The New York Pop-Up Book, manuals, videocassettes, computer disks, and financial materials.
Overall, the condition of the items is good. There are, in some cases, duplicates of materials. Documents are dated from 1997 through 2001, although many are not dated. More specific information may be found in each of the Series Descriptions.
Separated Material
The Nicole Miller scarves that came as part of the original collection (Series XII) have been moved to the N-YHS museum collection.
Arrangement Note
The arrangement of the collection follows that outlined in "Final Report for the archive of The New-York Historical Society prepared by Marie Salerno President, New York City 100." Series I – XIII are based on sections within the report and their folder titles correspond to the "Contents of File" lists. A copy of the report is available.
Some items are mentioned in the report but were not included in the donation. They are identified with an asterisk (*). In addition, there are items within the donation that are not mentioned in the report. Their titles are included within brackets [].
Series XIV – XVI are not described in the "Final Report…" See the Series Descriptions for arrangement of these materials.
Within several series, there are references to newspaper advertisements, clippings, reviews, etc. Materials of this type are located in Box 17, Folders 6 and 7 (Series XII) and in Box 18 (Series XVI). They are arranged by news source (e.g. The New York Times, New York Daily News) rather than by specific event.
The arrangement of the collection follows that outlined in "Final Report for the archive of The New-York Historical Society prepared by Marie Salerno President, New York City 100." Series I – XIII are based on sections within the report and their folder titles correspond to the "Contents of File" lists. A copy of the report is available.
There are items within the donation that are not mentioned in the report. Their titles are included within brackets [].
Series XIV – XVI are not described in the "Final Report…" See the Series Descriptions for arrangement of these materials.
Within several series, there are references to newspaper advertisements, clippings, reviews, etc. Materials of this type are located in Box 17, Folders 6 and 7 (Series XII) and in Box 18 (Series XVI). They are arranged by news source (e.g. The New York Times, The New York Daily News) rather than by specific event.
The New York City 100 Records are arranged into the following series:
Missing Title
Series I: Mission Statement & Final Report: January – December 1998
Series II: Background & Initial Planning (1995)
Series III: Public-Private Partnerships Established (1997)
Series IV: The Centennial Plan, January – December 1998
Series V: Centennial Logo
Series VI: Gracie Mansion Announcement Event
Series VII: Program Roster 1998
Series VIII: Mission Statements & Final Report, January – December 1999
Series IX: Program Roster 1999
Series X: Educational Outreach
Series XI: Centennial Sponsors and Media Partnerships, 1997-1999
Series XII: Public Relations and Advertising, 1998-1999
Series XIII: Products/Licensing
Series XIV: Accounting and Finance
Series XV: Video and Computer Archive
Series XVI: Press Clippings
Access Restrictions
Series XIV: Accounting and Finance, including boxes 10-13, contains confidential financial information and is restricted for 75 years. The rest of the collection is open to qualified researchers.
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Provenance
Donation, 2001.
Checks (bank checks); Photographs.; Memorandums.; Contracts.; Press releases.; Clippings (information artifacts); Invitations.; Programs (documents).; Transcripts.; Correspondence.; Compact discs.; New York (N.Y.); Posters.; Fireworks; Fund raising -- New York (State) -- New York.; Centennial celebrations, etc. -- New York (State) -- New York.; Bank statements.; Budgets; Invoices.; Graphic arts; Videocassettes.; Tax returns; Heiskell, Andrew; Salerno, Marie; Giuliani, Rudolph W.; Gotbaum, Betsy; Burns, Eric D., 1955-; New York Philharmonic; Jazz at Lincoln Center (Organization); New York Pops; Rudin, Lewis; Sulzberger, Arthur Ochs; Lewis, David Levering, 1936-; De Montebello, Philippe; Gregorian, Vartan; Ephron, Nora; Wasserstein, Wendy; Trillin, Calvin; Wolfe, Tom; Rich, Frank; Gelb, Arthur; Jackson, Kenneth T.; Hirschfeld, Al
- Series I: Mission Statement & Final Report: January – December 19, 1998-1999 (Box 1)
  Scope and Content
  This series introduces the organization, explains its reason for existence and provides highlights of its activity. It defines its function, outlines its leadership and includes a brief Final Report with highlights from January – December 1998.
  - a. Overview and Leadership, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - b. Final Report: January – December 1998 (New York City 100: Greater New York Centennial Celebration), 1999 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - c. NYC 100 Leadership, Identified, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - d. Staff Consultants Contact Sheet, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Series II: Background & Initial Planning (1995), 1995-1997, undated (Box 1)
  This series involves initial planning (1995) and includes copies of funding requests as well as a significant amount of early materials concerning the PBS documentary on New York's history that was planned for October 1998.
  - a. Early Draft of Mission Statement, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - b. New York History Year Overview, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - c. Correspondence Regarding Initial Planning Committee, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - d. New York History Year Funding Proposal, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - e. New York Documentary Press Release, 1995, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - f. NEH Funding Proposal, Undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - g. New York Documentary Outline, Undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Series III: Public-Private Partnerships Established (1997) (Box 1)
  Series III documents such 1997 activities as the Mayor's announcement of the Centennial celebration (May), the selection of Marie Salerno as the organization's president (July) and several early events including the first fundraiser (August). Folder h. 501(c) 3 Filing was empty and removed from the series.
  - a. Program for Mayor's City Hall Announcement of Centennial, May 5, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - b. Office of the Mayor, Press Release for Centennial, May 5, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - c. Arthur Gelb/The New York Times Breakfast Attendees List, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - d. The New York Times Breakfast Master Invitation List, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - e. Press Release Announcing Appointment of Marie Salerno, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - f. Salerno Appointment Article in The New York Times, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - g. Executed Contract for NYC 100 President, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - i. Salerno Biography and Photograph, Undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - j. Richard Edelman Invitation, First Fundraiser, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - [k. Letter Sent – Arthur Ochs Sulzberger and Andrew Heiskell to William F. Baker (WNET/Thirteen)], 1997 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Series IV: The Centennial Plan, January – December 1998 (Box 1)
  The focus of Series IV is the development of the Centennial Plan. The Advisory Committee roster and several drafts of the plan are contained within the series. Box 1, Folder 27 includes drafts along with requests for review and comment by various participants and edits provided by Professor Kenneth T. Jackson. In Box 1, Folder 26 is the plan developed by the City's Tourism Bureau for the Centennial year. Folder f. Final Plan / Mission Statements was empty and removed from the series.
  - a. Salerno NYC 100 Centennial Plan, Undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - b. NYC 100 Advisory Committee Membership Roster, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - c. Schuyler Chapin Memorandum to City's Cultural Community, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - d. Tourism Bureau's 1998 Centennial Marketing and Tourism Plan, Undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - e. Salerno NYC 100 Centennial Plan Drafts [7/14/97], 8/7/97 & 8/12/97, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Series V: Centennial Logo, 1997-1998, undated (Box 1, Box 16)
  The development of a logo for the New York City 100 Centennial is the subject of Series V which includes design submissions from the Tourism Bureau and Deluxe Design, as well as those of Pentagram, the creator of the selected graphic. Folder c. Pentagram Logo Design Modification for 1998 was empty and removed from the series.
  - a. Initial Letterhead, Undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - b. Pentagram Logo Design for 1998, Undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - d. Designs Submitted by Tourism Bureau (rejected), 1997 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - e. Designs Submitted by Deluxe Design (rejected), 1997 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - f. Graphic Identity Guidelines, Undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - g. Samples of Official NYC 100 Letterhead, Undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - h. Crain's New York Business Article on Sponsorship with New Logo: Dec 15-21, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - i. August 8th 1997 Presentation (Pentagram) (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - j. Stationary Mechanicals (Pentagram), 1998 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - [k. April 1998 Product Presentation (Pentagram)] (Box 16, Folder 3)
- Series VI: Gracie Mansion Announcement Event, 1997 (Box 2)
  Series VI provides complete documentation of the Centennial "kick-off" held at Gracie Mansion on September 8, 1997. Box 2, Folder 1 includes invitations, a program, articles from The New York Times, an invitation list and check list. Box 2, Folder 2, the program copy file, paints a picture of behind the scenes activities. A full list of guests can be found in Box 2, Folder 3 and an accounting of all expenses associated with the event is located in Box 2, Folder 4. Although not referenced in the final report, Box 2 Folder 7 contains thank you letters written by Marie Salerno to a number of participants. There are also several letters written to Ms. Salerno thanking her for the successful event. Folder g. Commemorative Cups and Napkins was removed from the series and its contents were transferred to the N-YHS museum collection.
  - a. "Save the Date" Letter, Invitation, Program, New York Times Articles, Master Invitation List and Check List, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - b. Program Copy File, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - c. Reception Guest Lists, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - d. Expenses, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - e. Press Kit, Salerno Press Release, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - f. Contact Sheets of Event Photos, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - [h. Thank You Letters], 1997 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Series VII: Program Roster 1998, 1997-1998 (Box 4, Box 3, Box 6, Box 5, Box 2, Box 18, Box 17, Box 16)
  Series VII describes programs and events planned for 1998, the Centennial Year. Each subseries focuses on a specific category of event.
  - Subseries 1: Consortium Events and Specially-Arranged Events, 1997-1998 (Box 3, Box 2, Box 16)
    This subseries documents a wide variety of events sponsored by the New York City 100 Consortium and other organizations throughout the City during 1998. Among the types of documents included are correspondence, facsimiles, handwritten notes, programs, advertisements, flyers, newspaper articles, schedules, transcripts of speeches and performances, lists of participants and event invitations.
    Among the items of interest are draft and final scripts for the television production "The City of Greater New York: The Story of Consolidation"; a copy of sections from the January, 1898, edition of The World's "The World Almanac and Encyclopedia" that identify opera houses, theaters and music halls located in Manhattan in 1898; and copies of the winning essays from a NYC 100 contest for school children.
    - a. Meeting File for October 22, 1997: Orchestras Deborah Dratell, Coordinator: Composer-in-residence, New York City Opera, 1997-1998 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - b. Meeting File for October 30, 1997: Theaters Rachell Chanoff, Coordinator, 1997-1998 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - c. Meeting File for November 5, 1997: Colleges & Universities Richard Mooney, Coordinator, 1997-1998 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - d. Meeting File for November 12, 1997: Films Nina Darnton, Coordinator, 1997-1998 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - e. Meeting at the New-York Historical Society November 20, 1997, Historians with Kenneth T. Jackson, 1997-1998 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - f. Meeting File for December 11, 1997: Consortium, 1997-1998 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - g. ABNY, Alliance for the Arts, Centennial Block, Crosswalks TV Network, Historic House Trust, Library of America, New York City Marathon, New York Historical Society, New York Public Library, South Street Seaport, Z100 Concert (1 of 4), 1998 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - g. ABNY, Alliance for the Arts, Centennial Block, Crosswalks TV Network, Historic House Trust, Library of America, New York City Marathon, New York Historical Society, New York Public Library, South Street Seaport, Z100 Concert (2 of 4), 1998 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - g. ABNY, Alliance for the Arts, Centennial Block, Crosswalks TV Network, Historic House Trust, Library of America, New York City Marathon, New York Historical Society, New York Public Library, South Street Seaport, Z100 Concert (3 of 4), 1997-1998 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - g. ABNY, Alliance for the Arts, Centennial Block, Crosswalks TV Network, Historic House Trust, Library of America, New York City Marathon, New York Historical Society, New York Public Library, South Street Seaport, Z100 Concert (4 of 4), 1997-1998 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - h. All Consortium Events, 1997-1998 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - i. Gardens (on Centennial Weekend), Organized by New York Botanical Garden, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - j. Walking Tours, Coordinated by Alexa Lalli and Peg Breen, 1997-1998 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - k. New Years' Eve 1998, NYC 100 Contest for Schoolchildren with Times Square BID, Including Centennial Logo Sew-on Patch for Children's Jackets, 1997-1998 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - l. Mayoral, Inauguration, Centennial New Year's Eve Gala and State of the City, 1997-1998 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - [m. Inauguration Press Clippings], 1997-1998 (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - [n. Original Mechanicals from The New York Times Ads January 1st, 1998] (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - [o. "New York, New York" Quiz, The New York Times January 4th, 1998] (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - [p. Sotheby's NYC Public School Art Show Poster], 1998 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Subseries 2: Centennial Weekend & Fireworks, 1997-1998 (Box 17, Box 5, Box 4, Box 16, Box 6)
    The weekend of June 19-21, 1998, was designated Centennial Weekend and involved activities in all five boroughs. The planning and execution of this series of events are described in Subseries 2. Items include agendas, photographs, press releases, correspondence, articles, schedules, invitations, parking permits, and the contents of various notebooks that were used to coordinate the events and inform the press. Among the interesting documents are a formal proposal from Fireworks by Grucci, Inc. for a multiple-location display (Box 4, Folder 6); a video cassette of the ceremony held at the New York Stock Exchange on June 19; and a copy of "The NYC100 Interactive Calendar Screensaver" that was part of a media handout. Within five folders (Box 4, Folder 9 through Box 5, Folder 4) are the contents of the Consortium Participants Master Binder with a description of every event held during the Centennial Weekend. Folder g. City Hall Press Conference/Target Tote Bag for Media Hand-out was removed from the series and its contents were transferred to the N-YHS museum collection.
    - a. City Hall Press Conference, June 12, 1998 Press Releases, Photographs and Memorandum (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - b. City Hall Files (1 of 3 – Bruce Teitlebaum), 1997-1998 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - b. City Hall Files (2 of 3 – Mayor's Office General), 1997-1998 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - b. City Hall Files (3 of 3 – City Commissioners), 1997-1998 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - c. Stock Exchange Opening Bell, June 19, 1998, Press Releases, Photographs and Correspondence (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - d. Centennial Fireworks, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - e. Press Information Binder (1 of 2), 1998 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - e. Press Information Binder (2 of 2), 1998 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - f. Consortium Participants Master Binder (1 of 5 – Bronx), 1998 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - f. Consortium Participants Master Binder (2 of 5 – Brooklyn), 1998 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - f. Consortium Participants Master Binder (3 of 5 – Manhattan), 1998 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - f. Consortium Participants Master Binder (4 of 5 – Queens), 1998 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - f. Consortium Participants Master Binder (5 of 5 – Staten Island), 1998 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - h. Staffer's Centennial Workbook (1 of 2), 1998 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - h. Staffer's Centennial Workbook (2 of 2), 1998 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - i. Video Cassette of Stock Exchange Ceremony, 1998 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - j. Mayor's Proclamation (Copy), 1998 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - j. Mayor's Proclamation (Original), 1998 (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - [k. Centennial Weekend Contact Sheets], 1998 (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - [l. The NYC 100 Interactive Calendar Screensaver], 1998 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - [m. Black Boards], 1998 (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - [n. Centennial Weekend Banner Designs], 1998 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - [o. Metropolitan Museum of Art Poster], 1998 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Subseries 3: Concert in Central Park, 1997-1998 (Box 18, Box 17, Box 6)
    This subseries focuses on a concert held July 10, 1998, on the Great Lawn in Central Park, including performances by the New York Pops, Jazz at Lincoln Center and the New York Philharmonic, along with others. Items include correspondence, newsletters, contract documents, press releases, participant lists, programs, tickets, passes and copies of newspaper articles. Folder e. Staff/Crew T-Shirts was removed from the series and its contents were transferred to the N-YHS museum collection.
    - a. Correspondence Relating to the Centennial Concert, 1997-1998 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - b. Concert Contracts, 1998 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - c. Folder Including Press Releases, RSVP's Program, Tickets and Passes, 1998 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - d. Press Clippings, Advertisements and Reviews, 1998 (Box 17, Box 18)
- Series VIII: Mission Statements & Final Report, January – December 1999, 1998-2000 (Box 7, Box 17, Volume BV, Box 6)
  Extending its celebration into 1999, the New York City 100 organization initiated "America Begins in New York." This second year of programming was based on the immigrant experience and its resulting diversity of views and cultural heritage across all five boroughs. Series VIII includes an overview of the 1999 events (Final Report – June 1, 2000) as well as some of the planning documentation.
  - 1. Mission Statement & Final Report, 1998-2000 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - 2. Planning Meetings January 7 and January 28, 1999 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - 3. Community Participation Campaign and Results, 1999 (Box 6, Folder 11)
- Series IX: Program Roster, 1999, 1999-2000 (Box 17, Box 6, Volume BV, Box 7)
  Series IX describes programs and events planned for 1999. Each subseries focuses on a specific category of event.
  - Subseries 1: America Begins in New York, 1999 (Box 17, Box 6)
    One of the activities planned for 1999 was a series of walking tours. This subseries contains advertisements, lists and schedules associated with the walks.
    - a. Walking Tours Program, 1999 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - b. Advertising Schedule, 1999 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - c. Advertisements, 1999 (Box 17, Folder 5, Folder 6)
  - Subseries 2: Journey Home Contest, 1999 (Box 6, Box 17)
    In 1999 the New York City 100 sponsored a contest called "Journey Home" with a grand prize of "A journey home (to any destination that American Airlines flies) including round trip airfare for two and five nights' accommodation." This subseries contains a list of the contest judges (Box 6 Folder 14) and several entry forms in a variety of formats – flyer, newspaper, and printed copy.
    - a. Judges List, 1999 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - b. Entry Forms, 1999 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - c. Poster for Contest, 1999 (Box 17, Folder 2)